<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39258383</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1096-9896</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The Journal of pathology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>J Pathol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Transcriptomic profiles of myxofibrosarcoma and undifferentiated pleomorphic sarcoma correlate with clinical and genomic features.</ArticleTitle><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/path.6347</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>Myxofibrosarcoma (MFS) and undifferentiated pleomorphic sarcoma (UPS) are two common and aggressive subtypes of soft tissue sarcoma. The aim of this study was to assess potential transcriptomic differences between MFS and UPS tumours and to evaluate the extent to which differences in gene expression profiles were associated with genomic and clinical features. The study included 162 patients with tumours diagnosed as MFS (N&#x2009;=&#x2009;62) or UPS (N&#x2009;=&#x2009;100). The patients had been diagnosed and treated at two Swedish sarcoma centres during a 30-year period. For gene expression profiling and gene fusion detection all tumours were analysed using RNA-sequencing and could be compared with data on clinical outcome (N&#x2009;=&#x2009;155), global copy number profiles (N&#x2009;=&#x2009;145), and gene mutations (N&#x2009;=&#x2009;128). Gene expression profiling revealed three transcriptomic clusters (TCs) without any clear separation of MFS and UPS. One TC was associated with longer metastasis-free survival. These tumours had lower tumour mutation burden (TMB), were enriched for a copy number signature representative of focal LOH and chromosomal instability on a diploid background, and were relatively immune-depleted. MFS and UPS showed extensive genomic overlap, with whole genome doubling occurring more frequently among the latter. The results support the idea that MFS and UPS tumours have largely overlapping genomic and transcriptomic features, with UPS tumours showing more aggressive behaviour and more complex genomes. Independently of the tumour type, clinically relevant subgroups were revealed by gene expression analysis, and the finding of multiple genomic subgroups strongly suggest the existence of subgroups of relevance to treatment stratification. &#xa9; 2024 The Author(s). The Journal of Pathology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of The Pathological Society of Great Britain and Ireland.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2024 The Author(s). The Journal of Pathology published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of The Pathological Society of Great Britain and Ireland.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mitra</LastName><ForeName>Shamik</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Clinical Genetics, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Farswan</LastName><ForeName>Akanksha</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University College London Cancer Institute, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Piccinelli</LastName><ForeName>Paul</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Genetics and Pathology, Office for Medical Services, Region Sk&#xe5;ne, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Sydow</LastName><ForeName>Saskia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Clinical Genetics, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Hesla</LastName><ForeName>Asle</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedics, Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Tsagkozis</LastName><ForeName>Panagiotis</ForeName><Initials>P</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedics, Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Vult von Steyern</LastName><ForeName>Fredrik</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Orthopedics, Sk&#xe5;ne University Hospital, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Almqvist</LastName><ForeName>Martin</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Surgery, Sk&#xe5;ne University Hospital, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Eriksson</LastName><ForeName>Mikael</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Oncology, Sk&#xe5;ne University Hospital, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Magnusson</LastName><ForeName>Linda</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Clinical Genetics, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Nilsson</LastName><ForeName>Jenny</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Clinical Genetics, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Pillay</LastName><ForeName>Nischalan</ForeName><Initials>N</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>University College London Cancer Institute, London, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Cellular and Molecular Pathology, Royal National Orthopaedic Hospital NHS Trust, Stanmore, UK.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mertens</LastName><ForeName>Fredrik</ForeName><Initials>F</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-6278-5232</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Division of Clinical Genetics, Department of Laboratory Medicine, Lund University, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Clinical Genetics and Pathology, Office for Medical Services, Region Sk&#xe5;ne, Lund, Sweden.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><GrantList CompleteYN="Y"><Grant><Agency>Kungliga Fysiografiska S&#xe4;llskapet i Lund</Agency><Country/></Grant><Grant><GrantID>232662Pj</GrantID><Agency>Cancerfonden</Agency><Country/></Grant><Grant><Agency>Swedish Cancer Society</Agency><Country/></Grant><Grant><Agency>Swedish Research Council</Agency><Country/></Grant><Grant><Agency>National Health Service of Sweden</Agency><Country/></Grant><Grant><Agency>Royal Physiographic Society in Lund</Agency><Country/></Grant></GrantList><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>J Pathol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0204634</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0022-3417</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM"><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">genomics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">myxofibrosarcoma</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">outcome</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">transcriptomics</Keyword><Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">undifferentiated pleomorphic sarcoma</Keyword></KeywordList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>7</Month><Day>1</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>4</Month><Day>2</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>6</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>5</Hour><Minute>3</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39258383</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/path.6347</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Mertens F, Johansson B, Fioretos T, et al. The emerging complexity of gene fusions in cancer. Nat Rev Cancer 2015; 15: 371&#x2013;381.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network. Comprehensive and integrated genomic characterization of adult soft tissue sarcomas. Cell 2017; 171: 950&#x2013;965.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>WHO Classification of Tumours of Soft Tissue and Bone (5th edn). IARC: Lyon, 2020; 606.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mitelman Database of Chromosome Aberrations and Gene Fusions in Cancer. Mitelman F, Johansson B and Mertens F (Eds.). Available from: https://mitelmandatabase.isb-cgc.org/.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Huang HY, Mentzel TDW, Shibata T. Myxofibrosarcoma. In WHO Classification of Tumours of Soft Tissue and Bone (5th edn). IARC: Lyon, 2020; 124&#x2013;126.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dei Tos AP, Mertens F, Pillay N. Undifferentiated sarcoma. In WHO Classification of Tumours of Soft Tissue and Bone (5th edn). IARC: Lyon, 2020; 318&#x2013;320.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele CD, Tarabichi M, Oukrif D, et al. Undifferentiated sarcomas develop through distinct evolutionary pathways. Cancer Cell 2019; 35: 441&#x2013;456.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Toulmonde M, Lucchesi C, Verbeke S, et al. High throughput profiling of undifferentiated pleomorphic sarcomas identifies two main subgroups with distinct immune profile, clinical outcome and sensitivity to targeted therapies. EBioMedicine 2020; 62: 103131.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Takeuchi Y, Yoshida K, Halik A, et al. The landscape of genetic aberrations in myxofibrosarcoma. Int J Cancer 2022; 151: 565&#x2013;577.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mertens F, Fletcher CDM, Dal Cin P, et al. Cytogenetic analysis of 46 pleomorphic soft tissue sarcomas and correlation with morphologic and clinical features: a report of the CHAMP study group. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 1998; 22: 16&#x2013;25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kresse SH, Ohnstad HO, Bjerkehagen B, et al. DNA copy number changes in human malignant fibrous histiocytomas by array comparative genomic hybridisation. PLoS One 2010; 5: e15378.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fletcher CDM, Bridge JA, Hogendoorn PCW, et al. (eds). WHO Classification of Tumours of Soft Tissue and Bone (4th edn). IARC: Lyon, 2013; 468.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trojani M, Contesso G, Coindre JM, et al. Soft&#x2010;tissue sarcomas of adults; study of pathological prognostic variables and definition of a histopathological grading system. Int J Cancer 1984; 33: 37&#x2013;42.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arbajian E, Puls F, Antonescu CR, et al. In&#x2010;depth genetic analysis of sclerosing epithelioid fibrosarcoma reveals recurrent genomic alterations and potential treatment targets. Clin Cancer Res 2017; 23: 7426&#x2013;7434.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Dobin A, Gingeras TR. Optimizing RNA&#x2010;seq mapping with STAR. Methods Mol Biol 2016; 1415: 245&#x2013;262.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li B, Dewey CN. RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA&#x2010;Seq data with or without a reference genome. BMC Bioinformatics 2011; 12: 323.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Soneson C, Love MI, Robinson MD. Differential analyses for RNA&#x2010;seq: transcript&#x2010;level estimates improve gene&#x2010;level inferences. F1000Res 2015; 4: 1521.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Xu T, Le TD, Liu L, et al. CancerSubtypes: an R/Bioconductor package for molecular cancer subtype identification, validation and visualization. Bioinformatics 2017; 33: 3131&#x2013;3133.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Love MI, Huber W, Anders S. Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA&#x2010;seq data with DESeq2. Genome Biol 2014; 15: 550.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Aran D, Hu Z, Butte AJ. xCell: digitally portraying the tissue cellular heterogeneity landscape. Genome Biol 2017; 18: 220.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang L, Forker L, Irlam JJ, et al. Validation of a hypoxia related gene signature in multiple soft tissue sarcoma cohorts. Oncotarget 2017; 9: 3946&#x2013;3955.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sydow S, Versleijen&#x2010;Jonkers YMH, et al. Genomic and transcriptomic characterization of desmoplastic small round cell tumors. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 2021; 60: 595&#x2013;603.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rasmussen M, Sundstr&#xf6;m M, Kultima H, et al. Allele&#x2010;specific copy number analysis of tumor samples with aneuploidy and tumor heterogeneity. Genome Biol 2011; 12: R108.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Loo P, Nordgard SH, Lingj&#xe6;rde OC, et al. Allele&#x2010;specific copy number analysis of tumors. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 2010; 107: 16910&#x2013;16915.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mandahl N, H&#xf6;glund M, Mertens F, et al. Cytogenetic aberrations in 188 benign and borderline adipose tissue tumors. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 1994; 9: 207&#x2013;215.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Walther C, Mayrhofer M, Nilsson J, et al. Genetic heterogeneity in rhabdomyosarcoma revealed by SNP array analysis. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 2016; 55: 3&#x2013;15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Steele CD, Abbasi A, Islam SMA, et al. Signatures of copy number alterations in human cancer. Nature 2022; 606: 984&#x2013;991.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Islam SMA, D&#xed;az&#x2010;Gay M, Wu Y, et al. Uncovering novel mutational signatures by de novo extraction with SigProfilerExtractor. Cell Genom 2022; 2: btad756.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>D'Angelo SP, Shoushtari AN, Agaram NP, et al. Prevalence of tumor&#x2010;infiltrating lymphocytes and PD&#x2010;L1 expression in the soft tissue sarcoma microenvironment. Hum Pathol 2015; 46: 357&#x2013;365.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sorbye SW, Kilvaer T, Valkov A, et al. High expression of CD20+ lymphocytes in soft tissue sarcomas is a positive prognostic indicator. Oncoimmunology 2012; 1: 75&#x2013;77.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Smolle MA, Herbsthofer L, Granegger B, et al. T&#x2010;regulatory cells predict clinical outcome in soft tissue sarcoma patients: a clinico&#x2010;pathological study. Br J Cancer 2021; 125: 717&#x2013;724.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>H&#xf8;land M, Berg KCG, Eilertsen IA, et al. Transcriptomic subtyping of malignant peripheral nerve sheath tumours highlights immune signatures, genomic profiles, patient survival and therapeutic targets. EBioMedicine 2023; 97: 104829.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Stransky N, Cerami E, Schalm S, et al. The landscape of kinase fusions in cancer. Nat Commun 2014; 5: 4846.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Delespaul L, Lesluyes T, P&#xe9;rot G, et al. Recurrent TRIO fusion in nontranslocation&#x2010;related sarcomas. Clin Cancer Res 2017; 23: 857&#x2013;867.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masuda H, Miller C, Koeffler HP, et al. Rearrangement of the p53 gene in human osteogenic sarcomas. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 1987; 84: 7716&#x2013;7719.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Chen X, Bahrami A, Pappo A, et al. Recurrent somatic structural variations contribute to tumorigenesis in pediatric osteosarcoma. Cell Rep 2014; 7: 104&#x2013;112.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sirohi D, Devine P, Grenert JP, et al. TP53 structural variants in metastatic prostatic carcinoma. PLoS One 2019; 14: e0218618.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Saba KH, Difilippo V, Kovac M, et al. Disruption of the TP53 locus in osteosarcoma leads to TP53 promoter gene fusions and restoration of parts of the TP53 signalling pathway. J Pathol 2024; 262: 147&#x2013;160.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mandahl N, Johansson B, Mertens F, et al. Disease&#x2010;associated patterns of disomic chromosomes in hyperhaploid neoplasms. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 2012; 51: 536&#x2013;544.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zheng S, Cherniack AD, Dewal N, et al. Comprehensive pan&#x2010;genomic characterization of adrenocortical carcinoma. Cancer Cell 2016; 29: 723&#x2013;736.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Arbajian E, K&#xf6;ster J, Vult von Steyern F, et al. Inflammatory leiomyosarcoma is a distinct tumor characterized by near&#x2010;haploidization, few somatic mutations, and a primitive myogenic gene expression signature. Mod Pathol 2018; 31: 93&#x2013;100.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yilmaz A, Peretz M, Sagi I, et al. Haploid human embryonic stem cells: half the genome, double the value. Cell Stem Cell 2016; 19: 569&#x2013;572.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sun JX, He Y, Sanford E, et al. A computational approach to distinguish somatic vs. germline origin of genomic alterations from deep sequencing of cancer specimens without a matched normal. PLoS Comput Biol 2018; 14: e1005965.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>