<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2024//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_240101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM"><PMID Version="1">39258352</PMID><DateRevised><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print-Electronic"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1521-1878</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><PubDate><Year>2024</Year><Month>Sep</Month><Day>11</Day></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>BioEssays : news and reviews in molecular, cellular and developmental biology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Bioessays</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Tissue-resident memory T cells: Harnessing their properties against infection for cancer treatment.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>e2400119</StartPage><MedlinePgn>e2400119</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1002/bies.202400119</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText>We have rapidly gained insights into the presence and function of T lymphocytes in non-lymphoid tissues, the tissue-resident memory T (T<sub>RM</sub>) cells. The central pillar of adaptive immunity has been expanded from classic central memory T cells giving rise to progeny upon reinfection and effector memory cells circulating through the blood and patrolling the tissues to include T<sub>RM</sub> cells that reside and migrate inside solid organs and tissues. Their development and maintenance have been studied in detail, providing exciting clues on how their unique properties used to fight infections may benefit therapies against solid tumors. We provide an overview of CD8 T<sub>RM</sub> cells and the properties that make them of interest for vaccination and cancer therapies.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2024 Wiley Periodicals LLC.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Fernandes</LastName><ForeName>Jo&#xe3;o</ForeName><Initials>J</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Medicina Molecular Jo&#xe3;o Lobo Antunes, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de Lisboa, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Veldhoen</LastName><ForeName>Marc</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1478-9562</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Medicina Molecular Jo&#xe3;o Lobo Antunes, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de Lisboa, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ferreira</LastName><ForeName>Cristina</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Instituto de Medicina Molecular Jo&#xe3;o Lobo Antunes, Faculdade de Medicina da Universidade de Lisboa, Lisbon, Portugal.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList><ArticleDate DateType="Electronic"><Year>2024</Year><Month>09</Month><Day>11</Day></ArticleDate></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>United States</Country><MedlineTA>Bioessays</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>8510851</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0265-9247</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>7</Hour><Minute>43</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>22</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2024</Year><Month>5</Month><Day>24</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2024</Year><Month>8</Month><Day>26</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2024</Year><Month>9</Month><Day>11</Day><Hour>4</Hour><Minute>53</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">39258352</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1002/bies.202400119</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>REFERENCES</Title><Reference><Citation>Schenkel, J. M., &amp; Masopust, D. (2014). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells. Immunity, 41, 886&#x2013;897. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2014.12.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaid, A., Mackay, L. K., Rahimpour, A., Braun, A., Veldhoen, M., Carbone, F. R., Manton, J. H., Heath, W. R., &amp; Mueller, S. N. (2014). Persistence of skin&#x2010;resident memory T cells within an epidermal niche. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 111, 5307&#x2013;5312. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1322292111</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Veldhoen, M., Blankenhaus, B., Konjar, S., &amp; Ferreira, C. (2018). Metabolic wiring of murine T cell and intraepithelial lymphocyte maintenance and activation. European Journal of Immunology, 48, 1430&#x2013;1440. https://doi.org/10.1002/eji.201646745</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hoytema van Konijnenburg, D. P., Reis, B. S., Pedicord, V. A., Farache, J., Victora, G. D., &amp; Mucida, D. (2017). Intestinal epithelial and intraepithelial T cell crosstalk mediates a dynamic response to infection. Cell, 171, 783&#x2013;794.e13. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2017.08.046</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Pan, Y., Tian, T., Park, C. O., Lofftus, S. Y., Mei, S., Liu, X., Luo, C., O'malley, J. T., Gehad, A., Teague, J. E., Divito, S. J., Fuhlbrigge, R., Puigserver, P., Krueger, J. G., Hotamisligil, G. S., Clark, R. A., &amp; Kupper, T. S. (2017). Survival of tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells requires exogenous lipid uptake and metabolism. Nature, 543, 252&#x2013;256. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature21379</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konjar, S., Frising, U. C., Ferreira, C., Hinterleitner, R., Mayassi, T., Zhang, Q., Blankenhaus, B., Haberman, N., Loo, Y., Guedes, J., Baptista, M., Innocentin, S., Stange, J., Strathdee, D., Jabri, B., &amp; Veldhoen, M. (2018). Mitochondria maintain controlled activation state of epithelial&#x2010;resident T lymphocytes. Science Immunology, 3, eaan2543. https://doi.org/10.1126/sciimmunol.aan2543</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konjar, S., &amp; Veldhoen, M. (2019). Dynamic metabolic state of tissue resident CD8 T cells. Frontiers in Immunology, 10, 1683. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2019.01683</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konjar, S., Ferreira, C., Carvalho, F. S., Figueiredo&#x2010;Campos, P., Fanczal, J., Ribeiro, S., Morais, V. A., &amp; Veldhoen, M. (2022). Intestinal tissue&#x2010;resident T cell activation depends on metabolite availability. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 119, e2202144119. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2202144119</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Konjar, S., Ficht, X., Iannacone, M., &amp; Veldhoen, M. (2022). Heterogeneity of tissue resident memory T cells. Immunology Letters, 245, 1&#x2013;7. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.imlet.2022.02.009</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mackay, L. K., Stock, A. T., Ma, J. Z., Jones, C. M., Kent, S. J., Mueller, S. N., Heath, W. R., Carbone, F. R., &amp; Gebhardt, T. (2012). Long&#x2010;lived epithelial immunity by tissue&#x2010;resident memory T (TRM) cells in the absence of persisting local antigen presentation. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 109, 7037&#x2013;7042. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1202288109</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shin, H., &amp; Iwasaki, A. (2012). A vaccine strategy that protects against genital herpes by establishing local memory T cells. Nature, 491, 463&#x2013;467. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature11522</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jiang, X., Clark, R. A., Liu, L., Wagers, A. J., Fuhlbrigge, R. C., &amp; Kupper, T. S. (2012). Skin infection generates non&#x2010;migratory memory CD8+ T(RM) cells providing global skin immunity. Nature, 483, 227&#x2013;231. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature10851</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaech, S. M., &amp; Cui, W. (2012). Transcriptional control of effector and memory CD8+ T cell differentiation. Nature Reviews Immunology, 12, 749&#x2013;761. https://doi.org/10.1038/nri3307</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kaech, S. M., &amp; Wherry, E. J. (2007). Heterogeneity and cell&#x2010;fate decisions in effector and memory CD8+ T cell differentiation during viral infection. Immunity, 27, 393&#x2013;405. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2007.08.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mackay, L. K., Rahimpour, A., Ma, J. Z., Collins, N., Stock, A. T., Hafon, M. L., Vega&#x2010;Ramos, J., Lauzurica, P., Mueller, S. N., Stefanovic, T., Tscharke, D. C., Heath, W. R., Inouye, M., Carbone, F. R., &amp; Gebhardt, T. (2013). The developmental pathway for CD103(+)CD8+ tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells of skin. Nature Immunology, 14, 1294&#x2013;1301. https://doi.org/10.1038/ni.2744</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mani, V., Bromley, S. K., Aijo, T., Mora&#x2010;Buch, R., Carrizosa, E., Warner, R. D., Hamze, M., Sen, D. R., Chasse, A. Y., Lorant, A., Griffith, J. W., Rahimi, R. A., Mcentee, C. P., Jeffrey, K. L., Marangoni, F., Travis, M. A., Lacy&#x2010;Hulbert, A., Luster, A. D., &amp; Mempel, T. R. (2019). Migratory DCs activate TGF&#x2010;beta to precondition naive CD8(+) T cells for tissue&#x2010;resident memory fate. Science, 366, eaav5728. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aav5728</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luster, A. D., Alon, R., &amp; von Andrian, U. H. (2005). Immune cell migration in inflammation: Present and future therapeutic targets. Nature Immunology, 6, 1182&#x2013;1190. https://doi.org/10.1038/ni1275</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masopust, D., Vezys, V., Marzo, A. L., &amp; Lefrancois, L. (2001). Preferential localization of effector memory cells in nonlymphoid tissue. Science, 291, 2413&#x2013;2417. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1058867</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Skon, C. N., Lee, J. Y., Anderson, K. G., Masopust, D., Hogquist, K. A., &amp; Jameson, S. C. (2013). Transcriptional downregulation of S1pr1 is required for the establishment of resident memory CD8+ T cells. Nature Immunology, 14, 1285&#x2013;1293. https://doi.org/10.1038/ni.2745</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bai, A., Hu, H., Yeung, M., &amp; Chen, J. (2007). Kruppel&#x2010;like factor 2 controls T cell trafficking by activating L&#x2010;selectin (CD62L) and sphingosine&#x2010;1&#x2010;phosphate receptor 1 transcription. Journal of Immunology, 178, 7632&#x2013;7639. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.178.12.7632</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferradini, L., Mackensen, A., Genevee, C., Bosq, J., Duvillard, P., Avril, M. F., &amp; Hercend, T. (1993). Analysis of T cell receptor variability in tumor&#x2010;infiltrating lymphocytes from a human regressive melanoma. Evidence for in situ T cell clonal expansion. The Journal of Clinical Investigation, 91, 1183&#x2013;1190. https://doi.org/10.1172/JCI116278</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Haanen, J. B., Baars, A., Gomez, R., Weder, P., Smits, M., De Gruijl, T. D., Von Blomberg, B. M. E., Bloemena, E., Scheper, R. J., Van Ham, S. M., Pinedo, H. M., &amp; Van Den Eertwegh, A. J. M. (2006). Melanoma&#x2010;specific tumor&#x2010;infiltrating lymphocytes but not circulating melanoma&#x2010;specific T cells may predict survival in resected advanced&#x2010;stage melanoma patients. Cancer Immunology, Immunotherapy, 55, 451&#x2013;458. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00262&#x2010;005&#x2010;0018&#x2010;5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Corbiere, V., Chapiro, J., Stroobant, V., Ma, W., Lurquin, C., Leth&#xe9;, B., Van Baren, N., Van Den Eynde, B. J., Boon, T., &amp; Coulie, P. G. (2011). Antigen spreading contributes to MAGE vaccination&#x2010;induced regression of melanoma metastases. Cancer Research, 71, 1253&#x2013;1262. https://doi.org/10.1158/0008&#x2010;5472.CAN&#x2010;10&#x2010;2693</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergsbaken, T., &amp; Bevan, M. J. (2015). Proinflammatory microenvironments within the intestine regulate the differentiation of tissue&#x2010;resident CD8(+) T cells responding to infection. Nature Immunology, 16, 406&#x2013;414. https://doi.org/10.1038/ni.3108</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hombrink, P., Helbig, C., Backer, R. A., Piet, B., Oja, A. E., Stark, R., Brasser, G., Jongejan, A., Jonkers, R. E., Nota, B., Basak, O., Clevers, H. C., Moerland, P. D., Amsen, D., &amp; Van Lier, R. A. W. (2016). Programs for the persistence, vigilance and control of human CD8(+) lung&#x2010;resident memory T cells. Nature Immunology, 17, 1467&#x2013;1478. https://doi.org/10.1038/ni.3589</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milner, J. J., Toma, C., Yu, B., Zhang, K., Omilusik, K., Phan, A. T., Wang, D., Getzler, A. J., Nguyen, T., Crotty, S., Wang, W., Pipkin, M. E., &amp; Goldrath, A. W. (2017). Runx3 programs CD8(+) T cell residency in non&#x2010;lymphoid tissues and tumours. Nature, 552, 253&#x2013;257. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature24993</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shiow, L. R., Rosen, D. B., Brdickova, N., Xu, Y., An, J., Lanier, L. L., Cyster, J. G., &amp; Matloubian, M. (2006). CD69 acts downstream of interferon&#x2010;alpha/beta to inhibit S1P1 and lymphocyte egress from lymphoid organs. Nature, 440, 540&#x2013;544. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature04606</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Freeman, B. E., Hammarlund, E., Raue, H. P., &amp; Slifka, M. K. (2012). Regulation of innate CD8+ T&#x2010;cell activation mediated by cytokines. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 109, 9971&#x2013;9976. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1203543109</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mackay, L. K., Braun, A., Macleod, B. L., Collins, N., Tebartz, C., Bedoui, S., Carbone, F. R., &amp; Gebhardt, T. (2015). Cutting edge: CD69 interference with sphingosine&#x2010;1&#x2010;phosphate receptor function regulates peripheral T cell retention. Journal of Immunology, 194, 2059&#x2013;2063. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1402256</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mackay, L. K., Minnich, M., Kragten, N. A., Liao, Y., Nota, B., Seillet, C., Zaid, A., Man, K., Preston, S., Freestone, D., Braun, A., Wynne&#x2010;Jones, E., Behr, F. M., Stark, R., Pellicci, D. G., Godfrey, D. I., Belz, G. T., Pellegrini, M., Gebhardt, T., &#x2026;, &amp; Van Gisbergen, K. P. J. M. (2016). Hobit and Blimp1 instruct a universal transcriptional program of tissue residency in lymphocytes. Science, 352, 459&#x2013;463. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aad2035</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yang, K., &amp; Kallies, A. (2021). Tissue&#x2010;specific differentiation of CD8(+) resident memory T cells. Trends in Immunology, 42, 876&#x2013;890. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.it.2021.08.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vieira Braga, F. A., Hertoghs, K. M., Kragten, N. A., Doody, G. M., Barnes, N. A., Remmerswaal, E. B. M., Hsiao, C. C., Moerland, P. D., Wouters, D., Derks, I. A. M., Van Stijn, A., Demkes, M., Hamann, J., Eldering, E., Nolte, M. A., Tooze, R. M., Ten Berge, I. J. M., Van Gisbergen, K. P. J. M., &amp; Van Lier, R. A. W. (2015). Blimp&#x2010;1 homolog Hobit identifies effector&#x2010;type lymphocytes in humans. European Journal of Immunology, 45, 2945&#x2013;2958. https://doi.org/10.1002/eji.201545650</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Behr, F. M., Kragten, N. A. M., Wesselink, T. H., Nota, B., Van Lier, R. A. W., Amsen, D., Stark, R., Hombrink, P., &amp; Van Gisbergen, K. P. J. M. (2019). Blimp&#x2010;1 rather than Hobit drives the formation of tissue&#x2010;resident memory CD8(+) T cells in the lungs. Frontiers in Immunology, 10, 400. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2019.00400</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kurd, N. S., He, Z., Louis, T. L., Milner, J. J., Omilusik, K. D., Jin, W., Tsai, M. S., Widjaja, C. E., Kanbar, J. N., Olvera, J. G., Tysl, T., Quezada, L. K., Boland, B. S., Huang, W. J., Murre, C., Goldrath, A. W., Yeo, G. W., &amp; Chang, J. T. (2020). Early precursors and molecular determinants of tissue&#x2010;resident memory CD8(+) T lymphocytes revealed by single&#x2010;cell RNA sequencing. Science Immunology, 5, eaaz6894. https://doi.org/10.1126/sciimmunol.aaz6894</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mackay, L. K., Wynne&#x2010;Jones, E., Freestone, D., Pellicci, D. G., Mielke, L. A., Newman, D. M., Braun, A., Masson, F., Kallies, A., Belz, G. T., &amp; Carbone, F. R. (2015). T&#x2010;box transcription factors combine with the cytokines TGF&#x2010;beta and IL&#x2010;15 to control tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cell fate. Immunity, 43, 1101&#x2013;1111. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2015.11.008</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Schenkel, J. M., Fraser, K. A., Casey, K. A., Beura, L. K., Pauken, K. E., Vezys, V., &amp; Masopust, D. (2016). IL&#x2010;15&#x2010;independent maintenance of tissue&#x2010;resident and boosted effector memory CD8 T cells. Journal of Immunology, 196, 3920&#x2013;3926. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1502337</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ciofani, M., Madar, A., Galan, C., Sellars, M., Mace, K., Pauli, F., Agarwal, A., Huang, W., Parkurst, C. N., Muratet, M., Newberry, K. M., Meadows, S., Greenfield, A., Yang, Y., Jain, P., Kirigin, F. K., Birchmeier, C., Wagner, E. F., Murphy, K. M., &#x2026;, &amp; Littman, D. R. (2012). A validated regulatory network for Th17 cell specification. Cell, 151, 289&#x2013;303. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2012.09.016</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebhardt, T., Wakim, L. M., Eidsmo, L., Reading, P. C., Heath, W. R., &amp; Carbone, F. R. (2009). Memory T cells in nonlymphoid tissue that provide enhanced local immunity during infection with herpes simplex virus. Nature Immunology, 10, 524&#x2013;530. https://doi.org/10.1038/ni.1718</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masopust, D., Choo, D., Vezys, V., Wherry, E. J., Duraiswamy, J., Akondy, R., Wang, J., Casey, K. A., Barber, D. L., Kawamura, K. S., Fraser, K. A., Webby, R. J., Brinkmann, V., Butcher, E. C., Newell, K. A., &amp; Ahmed, R. (2010). Dynamic T cell migration program provides resident memory within intestinal epithelium. The Journal of Experimental Medicine, 207, 553&#x2013;564. https://doi.org/10.1084/jem.20090858</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Fernandez&#x2010;Ruiz, D., Ng, W. Y., Holz, L. E., Ma, J. Z., Zaid, A., Wong, Y. C., Lau, L. S., Mollard, V., Cozijnsen, A., Collins, N., Li, J., Davey, G. M., Kato, Y., Devi, S., Skandari, R., Pauley, M., Manton, J. H., Godfrey, D. I., Braun, A., &#x2026;, &amp; Heath, W. R. (2016). Liver&#x2010;resident memory CD8(+) T cells form a front&#x2010;line defense against malaria liver&#x2010;stage infection. Immunity, 45, 889&#x2013;902. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2016.08.011</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cibrian, D., &amp; Sanchez&#x2010;Madrid, F. (2017). CD69: From activation marker to metabolic gatekeeper. European Journal of Immunology, 47, 946&#x2013;953. https://doi.org/10.1002/eji.201646837</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yu, C. I., Becker, C., Wang, Y., Marches, F., Helft, J., Leboeuf, M., Anguiano, E., Pourpe, S., Goller, K., Pascual, V., Banchereau, J., Merad, M., &amp; Palucka, K. (2013). Human CD1c+ dendritic cells drive the differentiation of CD103+ CD8+ mucosal effector T cells via the cytokine TGF&#x2010;beta. Immunity, 38, 818&#x2013;830. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2013.03.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Thom, J. T., Weber, T. C., Walton, S. M., Torti, N., &amp; Oxenius, A. (2015). The Salivary Gland Acts as a Sink for Tissue&#x2010;Resident Memory CD8(+) T Cells, Facilitating Protection from Local Cytomegalovirus Infection. Cell Reports, 13, 1125&#x2013;1136. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2015.09.082</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferreira, C., Barros, L., Baptista, M., Blankenhaus, B., Barros, A., Figueiredo&#x2010;Campos, P., Konjar, &#x160;., Lain&#xe9;, A., Kamenjarin, N., Stojanovic, A., Cerwenka, A., Probst, H. C., Marie, J. C., &amp; Veldhoen, M. (2020). Type 1 T(reg) cells promote the generation of CD8(+) tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells. Nature Immunology, 21, 766&#x2013;776. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41590&#x2010;020&#x2010;0674&#x2010;9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Christo, S. N., Evrard, M., Park, S. L., Gandolfo, L. C., Burn, T. N., Fonseca, R., Newman, D. M., Alexandre, Y. O., Collins, N., Zamudio, N. M., Souza&#x2010;Fonseca&#x2010;Guimaraes, F., Pellicci, D. G., Chisanga, D., Shi, W., Bartholin, L., Belz, G. T., Huntington, N. D., Lucas, A., Lucas, M., &#x2026;, &amp; Mackay, L. K. (2021). Discrete tissue microenvironments instruct diversity in resident memory T cell function and plasticity. Nature Immunology, 22, 1140&#x2013;1151. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41590&#x2010;021&#x2010;01004&#x2010;1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barros, L., Ferreira, C., &amp; Veldhoen, M. (2022). The fellowship of regulatory and tissue&#x2010;resident memory cells. Mucosal Immunology, 15, 64&#x2013;73. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41385&#x2010;021&#x2010;00456&#x2010;w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Barros, L., Piontkivska, D., Figueiredo&#x2010;Campos, P., Fanczal, J., Ribeiro, S. P., Baptista, M., Ariotti, S., Santos, N., Amorim, M. J., Pereira, C. S., Veldhoen, M., &amp; Ferreira, C. (2023). CD8(+) tissue&#x2010;resident memory T&#x2010;cell development depends on infection&#x2010;matching regulatory T&#x2010;cell types. Nature Communications, 14, 5579. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467&#x2010;023&#x2010;41364&#x2010;w</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McNamara, H. A., Cai, Y., Wagle, M. V., Sontani, Y., Roots, C. M., Miosge, L. A., O'connor, J. H., Sutton, H. J., Ganusov, V. V., Heath, W. R., Bertolino, P., Goodnow, C. G., Parish, I. A., Enders, A., &amp; Cockburn, I. A. (2017). Up&#x2010;regulation of LFA&#x2010;1 allows liver&#x2010;resident memory T cells to patrol and remain in the hepatic sinusoids. Science Immunology, 2, eaaj1996. https://doi.org/10.1126/sciimmunol.aaj1996</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Holz, L. E., Prier, J. E., Freestone, D., Steiner, T. M., English, K., Johnson, D. N., Mollard, V., Cozijnsen, A., Davey, G. M., Godfrey, D. I., Yui, K., Mackay, L. K., Lahoud, M. H., Caminschi, I., Mcfadden, G. I., Bertolino, P., Fernandez&#x2010;Ruiz, D., &amp; Heath, W. R. (2018). CD8(+) T cell activation leads to constitutive formation of liver tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells that seed a large and flexible niche in the liver. Cell Reports, 25, 68&#x2013;79.e4. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2018.08.094</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Khan, T. N., Mooster, J. L., Kilgore, A. M., Osborn, J. F., &amp; Nolz, J. C. (2016). Local antigen in nonlymphoid tissue promotes resident memory CD8+ T cell formation during viral infection. The Journal of Experimental Medicine, 213, 951&#x2013;966. https://doi.org/10.1084/jem.20151855</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Muschaweckh, A., Buchholz, V. R., Fellenzer, A., Hessel, C., K&#xf6;nig, P. A., Tao, S., Tao, R., Heikenw&#xe4;lder, M., Busch, D. H., Korn, T., Kastenm&#xfc;ller, W., Drexler, I., &amp; Gasteiger, G. (2016). Antigen&#x2010;dependent competition shapes the local repertoire of tissue&#x2010;resident memory CD8+ T cells. The Journal of Experimental Medicine, 213, 3075&#x2013;3086. https://doi.org/10.1084/jem.20160888</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Davies, B., Prier, J. E., Jones, C. M., Gebhardt, T., Carbone, F. R., &amp; Mackay, L. K. (2017). Cutting edge: Tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells generated by multiple immunizations or localized deposition provide enhanced immunity. Journal of Immunology, 198, 2233&#x2013;2237. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1601367</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Watanabe, R., Gehad, A., Yang, C., Scott, L. L., Teague, J. E., Schlapbach, C., Elco, C. P., Huang, V., Matos, T. R., Kupper, T. S., &amp; Clark, R. A. (2015). Human skin is protected by four functionally and phenotypically discrete populations of resident and recirculating memory T cells. Science Translational Medicine, 7, 279ra39. https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.3010302</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebhardt, T., Whitney, P. G., Zaid, A., Mackay, L. K., Brooks, A. G., Heath, W. R., Carbone, F. R., &amp; Mueller, S. N. (2011). Different patterns of peripheral migration by memory CD4+ and CD8+ T cells. Nature, 477, 216&#x2013;219. https://doi.org/10.1038/nature10339</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zaid, A., Hor, J. L., Christo, S. N., Groom, J. R., Heath, W. R., Mackay, L. K., &amp; Mueller, S. N. (2017). Chemokine receptor&#x2010;dependent control of skin tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cell formation. Journal of Immunology, 199, 2451&#x2013;2459. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1700571</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaide, O., Emerson, R. O., Jiang, X., Gulati, N., Nizza, S., Desmarais, C., Robins, H., Krueger, J. G., Clark, R. A., &amp; Kupper, T. S. (2015). Common clonal origin of central and resident memory T cells following skin immunization. Nature Medicine, 21, 647&#x2013;653. https://doi.org/10.1038/nm.3860</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Adachi, T., Kobayashi, T., Sugihara, E., Yamada, T., Ikuta, K., Pittaluga, S., Saya, H., Amagai, M., &amp; Nagao, K. (2015). Hair follicle&#x2010;derived IL&#x2010;7 and IL&#x2010;15 mediate skin&#x2010;resident memory T cell homeostasis and lymphoma. Nature Medicine, 21, 1272&#x2013;1279. https://doi.org/10.1038/nm.3962</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Milner, J. J., Toma, C., He, Z., Kurd, N. S., Nguyen, Q. P., Mcdonald, B., Quezada, L., Widjaja, C. E., Witherden, D. A., Crowl, J. T., Shaw, L. A., Yeo, G. W., Chang, J. T., Omilusik, K. D., &amp; Goldrath, A. W. (2020). Heterogenous populations of tissue&#x2010;resident CD8(+) T cells are generated in response to infection and malignancy. Immunity, 52, 808&#x2013;824.e7. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2020.04.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Van Kaer, L., &amp; Olivares&#x2010;Villagomez, D. (2018). Development, homeostasis, and functions of intestinal intraepithelial lymphocytes. Journal of Immunology, 200, 2235&#x2013;2244. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1701704</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zens, K. D., Chen, J. K., &amp; Farber, D. L. (2016). Vaccine&#x2010;generated lung tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells provide heterosubtypic protection to influenza infection. JCI Insight, 1, e85832. https://doi.org/10.1172/jci.insight.85832</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Casey, K. A., Fraser, K. A., Schenkel, J. M., Moran, A., Abt, M. C., Beura, L. K., Lucas, P. J., Artis, D., Wherry, E. J., Hogquist, K., Vezys, V., &amp; Masopust, D. (2012). Antigen&#x2010;independent differentiation and maintenance of effector&#x2010;like resident memory T cells in tissues. Journal of Immunology, 188, 4866&#x2013;4875. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1200402</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, N., &amp; Bevan, M. J. (2013). Transforming growth factor&#x2010;beta signaling controls the formation and maintenance of gut&#x2010;resident memory T cells by regulating migration and retention. Immunity, 39, 687&#x2013;696. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2013.08.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhou, A. C., Wagar, L. E., Wortzman, M. E., &amp; Watts, T. H. (2017). Intrinsic 4&#x2010;1BB signals are indispensable for the establishment of an influenza&#x2010;specific tissue&#x2010;resident memory CD8 T&#x2010;cell population in the lung. Mucosal Immunology, 10, 1294&#x2013;1309. https://doi.org/10.1038/mi.2016.124</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wu, T., Hu, Y., Lee, Y. T., Bouchard, K. R., Benechet, A., Khanna, K., &amp; Cauley, L. S. (2014). Lung&#x2010;resident memory CD8 T cells (TRM) are indispensable for optimal cross&#x2010;protection against pulmonary virus infection. Journal of Leukocyte Biology, 95, 215&#x2013;224. https://doi.org/10.1189/jlb.0313180</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>McMaster, S. R., Wein, A. N., Dunbar, P. R., Hayward, S. L., Cartwright, E. K., Denning, T. L., &amp; Kohlmeier, J. E. (2018). Pulmonary antigen encounter regulates the establishment of tissue&#x2010;resident CD8 memory T cells in the lung airways and parenchyma. Mucosal Immunology, 11, 1071&#x2013;1078. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41385&#x2010;018&#x2010;0003&#x2010;x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wakim, L. M., Smith, J., Caminschi, I., Lahoud, M. H., &amp; Villadangos, J. A. (2015). Antibody&#x2010;targeted vaccination to lung dendritic cells generates tissue&#x2010;resident memory CD8 T cells that are highly protective against influenza virus infection. Mucosal Immunology, 8, 1060&#x2013;1071. https://doi.org/10.1038/mi.2014.133</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laidlaw, B. J., Craft, J. E., &amp; Kaech, S. M. (2016). The multifaceted role of CD4(+) T cells in CD8(+) T cell memory. Nature Reviews Immunology, 16, 102&#x2013;111. https://doi.org/10.1038/nri.2015.10</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Laidlaw, B. J., Zhang, N., Marshall, H. D., Staron, M. M., &amp; Villadangos, J. A. (2014). CD4+ T cell help guides formation of CD103+ lung&#x2010;resident memory CD8+ T cells during influenza viral infection. Immunity, 41, 633&#x2013;645. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2014.09.007</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iborra, S., Martinez&#x2010;Lopez, M., Khouili, S. C., Enamorado, M., Cueto, F. J., Conde&#x2010;Garrosa, R., Del Fresno, C., &amp; Sancho, D. (2016). Optimal generation of tissue&#x2010;resident but not circulating memory T cells during viral infection requires crosspriming by DNGR&#x2010;1(+) dendritic cells. Immunity, 45, 847&#x2013;860. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2016.08.019</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lee, P. P., Yee, C., Savage, P. A., Fong, L., Cueto, F. J., Conde&#x2010;Garrosa, R., Del Fresno, C., &amp; Sancho, D. (1999). Characterization of circulating T cells specific for tumor&#x2010;associated antigens in melanoma patients. Nature Medicine, 5, 677&#x2013;685. https://doi.org/10.1038/9525</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Appay, V., Jandus, C., Voelter, V., Reynard, S., Coupland, S. E., Rimoldi, D., Lienard, D., Guillaume, P., Krieg, A. M., Cerottini, J. C., Romero, P., Leyvraz, S., Rufer, N., &amp; Speiser, D. E. (2006). New generation vaccine induces effective melanoma&#x2010;specific CD8+ T cells in the circulation but not in the tumor site. Journal of Immunology, 177, 1670&#x2013;1678. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.177.3.1670</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amsen, D., van Gisbergen, K., Hombrink, P., &amp; Van Lier, R. A. W. (2018). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells at the center of immunity to solid tumors. Nature Immunology, 19, 538&#x2013;546. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41590&#x2010;018&#x2010;0114&#x2010;2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Komdeur, F. L., Prins, T. M., Van De Wall, S., Plat, A., Wisman, G. B. A., Hollema, H., Daemen, T., Church, D. N., De Bruyn, M., &amp; Nijman, H. W. (2017). CD103+ tumor&#x2010;infiltrating lymphocytes are tumor&#x2010;reactive intraepithelial CD8+ T cells associated with prognostic benefit and therapy response in cervical cancer. Oncoimmunology, 6, e1338230. https://doi.org/10.1080/2162402X.2017.1338230</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Guo, X., Zhang, Y., Zheng, L., Zheng, C., Song, J., Zhang, Q., Kang, B., Liu, Z., Jin, L., Xing, R., Gao, R., Zhang, L., Dong, M., Hu, X., Ren, X., Kirchhoff, D., Roider, H. G., Yan, T., &amp; Zhang, Z. (2018). Global characterization of T cells in non&#x2010;small&#x2010;cell lung cancer by single&#x2010;cell sequencing. Nature Medicine, 24, 978&#x2013;985. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591&#x2010;018&#x2010;0045&#x2010;3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Savas, P., Virassamy, B., Ye, C., Salim, A., Mintoff, C. P., Caramia, F., Salgado, R., Byrne, D. J., Teo, Z. L., Dushyanthen, S., Byrne, A., Wein, L., Luen, S. J., Poliness, C., Nightingale, S. S., Skandarajah, A. S., Gyorki, D. E., Thornton, C. M., Beavis, P. A., &#x2026;, &amp; Loi, S. (2018). Single&#x2010;cell profiling of breast cancer T cells reveals a tissue&#x2010;resident memory subset associated with improved prognosis. Nature Medicine, 24, 986&#x2013;993. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41591&#x2010;018&#x2010;0078&#x2010;7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Malik, B. T., Byrne, K. T., Vella, J. L., Zhang, P., Shabaneh, T. B., Steinberg, S. M., Molodtsov, A. K., Bowers, J. S., Angeles, C. V., Paulos, C. M., Huang, Y. H., &amp; Turk, M. J. (2017). Resident memory T cells in the skin mediate durable immunity to melanoma. Science Immunology, 2, eaam6346. https://doi.org/10.1126/sciimmunol.aam6346</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, S. L., Buzzai, A., Rautela, J., Hor, J. L., Hochheiser, K., Effern, M., Mcbain, N., Wagner, T., Edwards, J., Mcconville, R., Wilmott, J. S., Scolyer, R. A., T&#xfc;ting, T., Palendira, U., Gyorki, D., Mueller, S. N., Huntington, N. D., Bedoui, S., H&#xf6;lzel, M., &#x2026;, &amp; Gebhardt, T. (2019). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory CD8(+) T cells promote melanoma&#x2010;immune equilibrium in skin. Nature, 565, 366&#x2013;371. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586&#x2010;018&#x2010;0812&#x2010;9</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Murray, T., Fuertes Marraco, S. A., Baumgaertner, P., Bordry, N., Cagnon, L., Donda, A., Romero, P., Verdeil, G., &amp; Speiser, D. E. (2016). Very late antigen&#x2010;1 marks functional tumor&#x2010;resident CD8 T cells and correlates with survival of melanoma patients. Frontiers in Immunology, 7, 573. https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2016.00573</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Simoni, Y., Becht, E., Fehlings, M., Loh, C. Y., Koo, S. L., Teng, K. W. W., Yeong, J. P. S., Nahar, R., Zhang, T., Kared, H., Duan, K., Ang, N., Poidinger, M., Lee, Y. Y., Larbi, A., Khng, A. J., Tan, E., Fu, C., Mathew, R., &#x2026;, &amp; Newell, E. W. (2018). Bystander CD8(+) T cells are abundant and phenotypically distinct in human tumour infiltrates. Nature, 557, 575&#x2013;579. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586&#x2010;018&#x2010;0130&#x2010;2</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bengsch, B., Ohtani, T., Khan, O., Setty, M., Manne, S., O'brien, S., Gherardini, P. F., Herati, R. S., Huang, A. C., Chang, K. M., Newell, E. W., Bovenschen, N., Pe'er, D., Albelda, S. M., &amp; Wherry, E. J. (2018). Epigenomic&#x2010;guided mass cytometry profiling reveals disease&#x2010;specific features of exhausted CD8 T cells. Immunity, 48, 1029&#x2013;1045.e5. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2018.04.026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, L., Yu, X., Zheng, L., Zhang, Y., Li, Y., Fang, Q., Gao, R., Kang, B., Zhang, Q., Huang, J. Y., Konno, H., Guo, X., Ye, Y., Gao, S., Wang, S., Hu, X., Ren, X., Shen, Z., Ouyang, W., &amp; Zhang, Z. (2018). Lineage tracking reveals dynamic relationships of T cells in colorectal cancer. Nature, 564, 268&#x2013;272. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586&#x2010;018&#x2010;0694&#x2010;x</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gebhardt, T., Palendira, U., Tscharke, D. C., &amp; Bedoui, S. (2018). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells in tissue homeostasis, persistent infection, and cancer surveillance. Immunological Reviews, 283, 54&#x2013;76. https://doi.org/10.1111/imr.12650</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Byrne, A., Savas, P., Sant, S., Li, R., Virassamy, B., Luen, S. J., Beavis, P. A., Mackay, L. K., Neeson, P. J., &amp; Loi, S. (2020). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells in breast cancer control and immunotherapy responses. Nature Reviews Clinical Oncology, 17, 341&#x2013;348. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41571&#x2010;020&#x2010;0333&#x2010;y</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Zhang, Y., Kurupati, R., Liu, L., Zhou, X. Y., Zhang, G., Hudaihed, A., Filisio, F., Giles&#x2010;Davis, W., Xu, X., Karakousis, G. C., Schuchter, L. M., Xu, W., Amaravadi, R., Xiao, M., Sadek, N., Krepler, C., Herlyn, M., Freeman, G. J., Rabinowitz, J. D., &amp; Ertl, H. C. J. (2017). Enhancing CD8(+) T cell fatty acid catabolism within a metabolically challenging tumor microenvironment increases the efficacy of melanoma immunotherapy. Cancer Cell, 32, 377&#x2013;391.e9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ccell.2017.08.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bian, Y., Li, W., Kremer, D. M., Sajjakulnukit, P., Li, S., Crespo, J., Nwosu, Z. C., Zhang, L., Czerwonka, A., Paw&#x142;owska, A., Xia, H., Li, J., Liao, P., Yu, J., Vatan, L., Szeliga, W., Wei, S., Grove, S., Liu, J. R., &#x2026;, &amp; Zou, W. (2020). Cancer SLC43A2 alters T cell methionine metabolism and histone methylation. Nature, 585, 277&#x2013;282. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586&#x2010;020&#x2010;2682&#x2010;1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Masopust, D., &amp; Schenkel, J. M. (2013). The integration of T cell migration, differentiation and function. Nature Reviews Immunology, 13, 309&#x2013;320. https://doi.org/10.1038/nri3442</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, S. L., Gebhardt, T., &amp; Mackay, L. K. (2019). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells in cancer immunosurveillance. Trends in Immunology, 40, 735&#x2013;747. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.it.2019.06.002</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mlecnik, B., Bindea, G., Angell, H. K., Sasso, M. S., Obenauf, A. C., Fredriksen, T., Lafontaine, L., Bilocq, A. M., Kirilovsky, A., Tosolini, M., Waldner, M., Berger, A., Fridman, W. H., Rafii, A., Valge&#x2010;Archer, V., Pag&#xe8;s, F., Speicher, M. R., &amp; Galon, J. (2014). Functional network pipeline reveals genetic determinants associated with in situ lymphocyte proliferation and survival of cancer patients. Science Translational Medicine, 6, 228ra37. https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.3007240</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Edwards, J., Wilmott, J. S., Madore, J., Gide, T. N., Quek, C., Tasker, A., Ferguson, A., Chen, J., Hewavisenti, R., Hersey, P., Gebhardt, T., Weninger, W., Britton, W. J., Saw, R. P. M., Thompson, J. F., Menzies, A. M., Long, G. V., Scolyer, R. A., &amp; Palendira, U. (2018). CD103(+) tumor&#x2010;resident CD8(+) T cells are associated with improved survival in immunotherapy&#x2010;naive melanoma patients and expand significantly during anti&#x2010;PD&#x2010;1 treatment. Clinical Cancer Research, 24, 3036&#x2013;3045. https://doi.org/10.1158/1078&#x2010;0432.CCR&#x2010;17&#x2010;2257</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rosato, P. C., Lotfi&#x2010;Emran, S., Joag, V., Wijeyesinghe, S., Quarnstrom, C. F., Degefu, H. N., Nedellec, R., Schenkel, J. M., Beura, L. K., Hangartner, L., Burton, D. R., &amp; Masopust, D. (2023). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells trigger rapid exudation and local antibody accumulation. Mucosal Immunology, 16(1), 17&#x2013;26. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mucimm.2022.11.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mami&#x2010;Chouaib, F., Blanc, C., Corgnac, S., Hans, S., Malenica, I., Granier, C., Tihy, I., &amp; Tartour, E. (2018). Resident memory T cells, critical components in tumor immunology. Journal for Immunotherapy of Cancer, 6, 87. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40425&#x2010;018&#x2010;0399&#x2010;6</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ganesan, A. P., Clarke, J., Wood, O., Garrido&#x2010;Martin, E. M., Chee, S. J., Mellows, T., Samaniego&#x2010;Castruita, D., Singh, D., Seumois, G., Alzetani, A., Woo, E., Friedmann, P. S., King, E. V., Thomas, G. J., Sanchez&#x2010;Elsner, T., Vijayanand, P., &amp; Ottensmeier, C. H. (2017). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory features are linked to the magnitude of cytotoxic T cell responses in human lung cancer. Nature Immunology, 18, 940&#x2013;950. https://doi.org/10.1038/ni.3775</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Djenidi, F., Adam, J., Goubar, A., Durgeau, A., Meurice, G., De Montpr&#xe9;ville, V., Validire, P., Besse, B., &amp; Mami&#x2010;Chouaib, F. (2015). CD8+CD103+ tumor&#x2010;infiltrating lymphocytes are tumor&#x2010;specific tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells and a prognostic factor for survival in lung cancer patients. Journal of Immunology, 194, 3475&#x2013;3486. https://doi.org/10.4049/jimmunol.1402711</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mattei, F., Andreone, S., Marone, G., Gambardella, A. R., Loffredo, S., Varricchi, G., &amp; Schiavoni, G. (2020). Eosinophils in the tumor microenvironment. Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology, 1273, 1&#x2013;28. https://doi.org/10.1007/978&#x2010;3&#x2010;030&#x2010;49270&#x2010;0_1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Amersfoort, J., Eelen, G., &amp; Carmeliet, P. (2022). Immunomodulation by endothelial cells&#x2014;partnering up with the immune system? Nature Reviews Immunology, 22, 576&#x2013;588. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41577&#x2010;022&#x2010;00694&#x2010;4</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Li, X., Zhai, J., Shen, Y., Zhang, T., Wang, Y., He, Y., You, Q., &amp; Shen, L. (2022). Tumor&#x2010;derived IL&#x2010;8 facilitates lymph node metastasis of gastric cancer via PD&#x2010;1 up&#x2010;regulation in CD8(+) T cells. Cancer Immunology, Immunotherapy, 71, 3057&#x2013;3070. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00262&#x2010;022&#x2010;03223&#x2010;3</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Farhood, B., Najafi, M., &amp; Mortezaee, K. (2019). CD8(+) cytotoxic T lymphocytes in cancer immunotherapy: A review. Journal of Cellular Physiology, 234, 8509&#x2013;8521. https://doi.org/10.1002/jcp.27782</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Plitas, G., Konopacki, C., Wu, K., Bos, P. D., Morrow, M., Putintseva, E. V., Chudakov, D. M., &amp; Rudensky, A. Y. (2016). Regulatory T cells exhibit distinct features in human breast cancer. Immunity, 45, 1122&#x2013;1134. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2016.10.032</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kalia, V., Penny, L. A., Yuzefpolskiy, Y., Baumann, F. M., &amp; Sarkar, S. (2015). Quiescence of memory CD8(+) T cells is mediated by regulatory T cells through inhibitory receptor CTLA&#x2010;4. Immunity, 42, 1116&#x2013;1129. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2015.05.023</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wherry, E. J., Ha, S. J., Kaech, S. M., Haining, W. N., Sarkar, S., Kalia, V., Subramaniam, S., Blattman, J. N., Barber, D. L., &amp; Ahmed, R. (2007). Molecular signature of CD8+ T cell exhaustion during chronic viral infection. Immunity, 27, 670&#x2013;684. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.immuni.2007.09.006</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Boddupalli, C. S., Bar, N., Kadaveru, K., Krauthammer, M., Pornputtapong, N., Mai, Z., Ariyan, S., Narayan, D., Kluger, H., Deng, Y., Verma, R., Das, R., Bacchiocchi, A., Halaban, R., Sznol, M., Dhodapkar, M. V., &amp; Dhodapkar, K. M. (2016). Interlesional diversity of T cell receptors in melanoma with immune checkpoints enriched in tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells. JCI Insight, 1, e88955. https://doi.org/10.1172/jci.insight.88955</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Park, S. L., Zaid, A., Hor, J. L., Christo, S. N., Prier, J. E., Davies, B., Alexandre, Y. O., Gregory, J. L., Russell, T. A., Gebhardt, T., Carbone, F. R., Tscharke, D. C., Heath, W. R., Mueller, S. N., &amp; Mackay, L. K. (2018). Local proliferation maintains a stable pool of tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells after antiviral recall responses. Nature Immunology, 19, 183&#x2013;191. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41590&#x2010;017&#x2010;0027&#x2010;5</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Shwetank, A. H. A., Frost, E. L., Schmitz, H. M., Mockus, T. E., Youngblood, B. A., &amp; Lukacher, A. E. (2017). Maintenance of PD&#x2010;1 on brain&#x2010;resident memory CD8 T cells is antigen independent. Immunology and Cell Biology, 95, 953&#x2013;959. https://doi.org/10.1038/icb.2017.62</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gamradt, P., Laoubi, L., Nosbaum, A., Mutez, V., Lenief, V., Grande, S., Redoul&#xe8;s, D., Schmitt, A. M., Nicolas, J. F., &amp; Vocanson, M. (2019). Inhibitory checkpoint receptors control CD8(+) resident memory T cells to prevent skin allergy. The Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology, 143, 2147&#x2013;2157.e9. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaci.2018.11.048</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Memon, H., &amp; Patel, B. M. (2019). Immune checkpoint inhibitors in non&#x2010;small cell lung cancer: A bird's eye view. Life Sciences, 233, 116713. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lfs.2019.116713</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Lange, J., Rivera&#x2010;Ballesteros, O., &amp; Buggert, M. (2021). Human mucosal tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells in health and disease. Mucosal Immunology, 15, 389&#x2013;397. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41385&#x2010;021&#x2010;00467&#x2010;7</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Navarro&#x2010;Fernandez, I., Gonzalez&#x2010;Vela, C., Gomez&#x2010;Fernandez, C., Duran&#x2010;Vian, C., Reguero, L., &amp; Gonzalez&#x2010;Lopez, M. (2021). Vitiligo&#x2010;like depigmentation in a patient undergoing treatment with nivolumab for advanced renal&#x2010;cell carcinoma. Acta Dermatovenerologica Croatica, 291, 54&#x2013;55.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Yun, S. J., Oh, I. J., Park, C. K., Kim, Y. C., Kim, H. B., Kim, H. K., Hong, A. R., Kim, I. Y., Ahn, S. J., Na, K. J., &amp; Choi, Y. D. (2020). Vitiligo&#x2010;like depigmentation after pembrolizumab treatment in patients with non&#x2010;small cell lung cancer: A case report. Translational Lung Cancer Research, 9, 1585&#x2013;1590. https://doi.org/10.21037/tlcr&#x2010;20&#x2010;386</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Han, J., Zhao, Y., Shirai, K., Molodtsov, A., Kolling, F. W., Fisher, J. L., Zhang, P., Yan, S., Searles, T. G., Bader, J. M., Gui, J., Cheng, C., Ernstoff, M. S., Turk, M. J., &amp; Angeles, C. V. (2021). Resident and circulating memory T cells persist for years in melanoma patients with durable responses to immunotherapy. Nature Cancer, 2, 300&#x2013;311. https://doi.org/10.1038/s43018&#x2010;021&#x2010;00180&#x2010;1</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Workel, H. H., Komdeur, F. L., Wouters, M. C., Plat, A., Klip, H. G., Eggink, F. A., Wisman, G. B. A., Arts, H. J. G., Oonk, M. H. M., Mourits, M. J. E., Yigit, R., Versluis, M., Duiker, E. W., Hollema, H., De Bruyn, M., &amp; Nijman, H. W. (2016). CD103 defines intraepithelial CD8+ PD1+ tumour&#x2010;infiltrating lymphocytes of prognostic significance in endometrial adenocarcinoma. European Journal of Cancer, 60, 1&#x2013;11. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejca.2016.02.026</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hartana, C. A., Ahlen Bergman, E., Broome, A., Berglund, S., Johansson, M., Alamdari, F., Jakubczyk, T., Huge, Y., Aljabery, F., Palmqvist, K., Holmstr&#xf6;m, B., Glise, H., Riklund, K., Sherif, A., &amp; Winqvist, O. (2018). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells are epigenetically cytotoxic with signs of exhaustion in human urinary bladder cancer. Clinical and Experimental Immunology, 194, 39&#x2013;53. https://doi.org/10.1111/cei.13183</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Virassamy, B., Caramia, F., Savas, P., Sant, S., Wang, J., Christo, S. N., Byrne, A., Clarke, K., Brown, E., Teo, Z. L., Von Scheidt, B., Freestone, D., Gandolfo, L. C., Weber, K., Teply&#x2010;Szymanski, J., Li, R., Luen, S. J., Denkert, C., Loibl, S., &#x2026;, &amp; Loi, S. (2023). Intratumoral CD8(+) T cells with a tissue&#x2010;resident memory phenotype mediate local immunity and immune checkpoint responses in breast cancer. Cancer Cell, 41, 585&#x2013;601.e8. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ccell.2023.01.004</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Luoma, A. M., Suo, S., Wang, Y., Gunasti, L., Porter, C. B. M., Nabilsi, N., Tadros, J., Ferretti, A. P., Liao, S., Gurer, C., Chen, Y. H., Criscitiello, S., Ricker, C. A., Dionne, D., Rozenblatt&#x2010;Rosen, O., Uppaluri, R., Haddad, R. I., Ashenberg, O., Regev, A., &#x2026; Wucherpfennig, K. W. (2022). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory and circulating T cells are early responders to pre&#x2010;surgical cancer immunotherapy. Cell, 185, 2918&#x2013;2935.e29. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2022.06.018</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bergsbaken, T., Bevan, M. J., &amp; Fink, P. J. (2017). Local inflammatory cues regulate differentiation and persistence of CD8(+) tissue&#x2010;resident memory T cells. Cell Reports, 19, 114&#x2013;124. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2017.03.031</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jung, I. Y., Noguera&#x2010;Ortega, E., Bartoszek, R., Collins, S. M., Williams, E., Davis, M., Jadlowsky, J. K., Plesa, G., Siegel, D. L., Chew, A., Levine, B. L., Berger, S. L., Moon, E. K., Albelda, S. M., &amp; Fraietta, J. A. (2023). Tissue&#x2010;resident memory CAR T cells with stem&#x2010;like characteristics display enhanced efficacy against solid and liquid tumors. Cell Reports Medicine, 4, 101053. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.xcrm.2023.101053</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>